<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Confessions of a Futbol Revolutionist</title>
<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2015-12-15T05:01:06+00:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Kevin Schachter</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>kevinschachter@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Social Justice through the Shadow State: Examining the Progressive Potential of Delivering Social Welfare Supports through the Non-profit Sector]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/proposal-outline" />
  <id>/proposal-outline</id>
  <published>2015-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Kevin Schachter</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kevinschachter@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dawn of the neoliberal era in the last decades of the 20th century ushered in a fundamental restructuring of the state apparatus, notably including a retrenchment of the public social welfare regimes that had been developed earlier in the century. A primary means by which restructuring has occurred is through devolution of responsibility for social services from the state to the private and non-profit sectors. According to &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989, 201)&lt;/span&gt;, this devolution has led to the formation of a “shadow state apparatus” consisting of non-governmental organizations that are endowed with responsibility to provide collective social welfare supports and are situated outside of the statutory welfare regime. While &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989, 202)&lt;/span&gt; finds that theorists from across the political spectrum have advocated for non-governmental organizations to assume a greater role in delivering social welfare supports, the literature abounds with criticisms which highlight that a primary motivation for and effect of devolution is to support the ongoing neoliberal project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;critiques-of-devolution&quot;&gt;Critiques of Devolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decrease in social welfare
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some geographic areas and organizations have greater access to resources and services than others, while vulnerable communities may have less access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reliance upon user fees is especially problematic for vulnerable communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to withdraw funding from NGOs than to eliminate direct government programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reduces government accountability for social inequality and associated problems &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;macdonald2011&quot;&gt;(MacDonald 2011)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Furthers the colonization of society with neoliberal ways of being
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizations must compete for funding
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Branding and marketing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business and entrepreneurial activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restrictions on activities in order to remain fundable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NGO industrial complex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress on efficiency
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower wages and costs than public sector employment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible labour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourages the development of neoliberal dispositions among citizens accessing supports
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model of self-help instead of public welfare and basic entitlement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;progressive-potential&quot;&gt;Progressive Potential&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May increase local autonomy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political clout of the voluntary sector could pressure the state for increased entitlements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could extend the range of social welfare services available rather than fill service gaps caused by retrenchment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can mobilize resistance among vulnerable groups and advocates of social justice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human-scale, community organizations rather than “iron cage” government bureaucracies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;research-question&quot;&gt;Research Question&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This project will assess the progressive potential of delivering social welfare supports through the non-profit sector, and explicate factors that contribute to and counteract the voluntary sector’s capacity to work for progressive social change.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can non-profit social welfare organizations contribute to broader social transformation beyond immediate service delivery?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can shadow state organizations deliver services in a manner that is compatible with a broader vision for social change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What factors contribute to and counteract the non-profit sector’s capacity to contribute to progressive social change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the benefits and drawbacks of delivering social welfare services/supports through the voluntary sector?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there additional benefits to service recipients that derive from accessing supports from non-profit organizations rather than from government institutions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;theoretical-lens&quot;&gt;Theoretical Lens&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will draw upon and apply two theories of radical social change to assess the progressive potential of providing social welfare supports through the non-profit sector: strategic and prefigurative politics.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategic:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What factors contribute to and counteract the sector’s capacity to advocate for systemic, structural change in government programs and policies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefigurative:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What factors contribute to and counteract the sector’s capacity to contribute towards changes in the everyday lives of community members, including cultural and relational transformation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To what extent can prefigurative politics be practiced in the shadow state?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there an affinity between prefigurative politics and the model of social change being practiced by social welfare NGOs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the devolution of social welfare service provision to the voluntary sector provide additional opportunities for the practice of prefigurative politics in the process of service deliver?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tension between these two theories concerning the role that formal organizations should play in efforts to achieve radical social change.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can non-profit social welfare service providers be leveraged by movements for radical social change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This project will draw upon a qualititative research methodology and employ three research methods:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literature review
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synthesizing and connecting literature on the benefits and drawbacks of devolving social welfare services to the shadow state, and how devolution can contribute to or counteract the realization of social justice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literature on:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The shadow state and social service devolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radical social change, prefigurative politics, participatory democracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People-centered systems / systems that work well from the perspective of the user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autoethnography
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An autoethnographical analysis of my experience developing and delivering social welfare programs to low-income communities as a program co-ordinator at SEED Winnipeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informal expert interviews
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informal expert interviews with program delivery staff and directors at SEED Winnipeg, who have experience developing, managing, and delivering community-based social welfare programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-macdonald2011&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacDonald, Fiona. 2011. “Indigenous Peoples and Neoliberal Privatization in Canada: Opportunities, Cautions and Constraints.” &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Political Science/Revue Canadienne de Science Politique&lt;/em&gt; 44 (02): 257–73. &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1017/S000842391100014X&quot;&gt;doi:10.1017/S000842391100014X&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-wolch1989&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wolch, Jennifer R. 1989. “The Shadow State : Transformations in the Voluntary Sector.” In &lt;em&gt;The Power of Geography : How Territory Shapes Social Life&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jennifer R. Wolch and Michael J. Dear, 197–221. Boston: Unwin Hyman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/proposal-outline&quot;&gt;Social Justice through the Shadow State: Examining the Progressive Potential of Delivering Social Welfare Supports through the Non-profit Sector&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Kevin Schachter at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Confessions of a Futbol Revolutionist&lt;/a&gt; on December 14, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>