<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Confessions of a Futbol Revolutionist</title>
<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2016-03-23T04:02:03+01:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Kevin Schachter</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>kevinschachter@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Voluntary Sector Social Service Provision]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/proposal-draft" />
  <id>/proposal-draft</id>
  <published>2016-03-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-03-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Kevin Schachter</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kevinschachter@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The important role played by non-profit organizations in delivering social services to the population has been highlighted by &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;Salamon (1995)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989)&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;hall1998&quot;&gt;Hall and Reed (1998)&lt;/span&gt;, who have quantified the scale of the non-profit social service sector in terms of number of organizations and employees, and amount of government funds received.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholars have advanced a variety of theories to explain the enormous growth in the non-profit sector’s role in delivering social services and to explicate the benefits and drawbacks of this model of collective service provision. Traditionally, the presence of the voluntary sector in social service provision has been considered to be the result of a combined “market failure,” characterized by an inability for consumers to privately procure needed services, and a “government failure” of the state to collectively provide these services through public welfare state institutions &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;(Salamon 1995)&lt;/span&gt;. According to these theories, the voluntary sector steps in to provide social services when the state and market fail to do so. &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;Salamon (1995)&lt;/span&gt; argues against these reductive explanations and counterposes that much of the growth of voluntary sector social service provision is the result of government investment in the sector through partnerships between state funding agencies and non-profit organizations who utilize public funds to deliver services. Salamon situates these partnerships within a larger trend of “third-party government”, by which the role of government as a fundraiser and funder has become separated from its role as a direct service provider &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;(Salamon 1995 PAGE)&lt;/span&gt;. In support of this claim, Salamon finds that the massive growth in the reach and size of the U.S. federal government in the period of welfare state expansion between the 1950s and 1980s was enacted through partnerships between the federal government, lower levels of government, for-profit industry, and the non-profit sector. In this period, government growth occurred primarily in its capacity to procure and distribute funds, without a concomitant increase in the scale of direct government program delivery. Instead, these responsibilities became increasingly assumed by private and non-profit organizations, who utilized public funds to deliver services through private institutional forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;milward1994&quot;&gt;Milward (1994)&lt;/span&gt; conceives that this split between the government’s active role in procuring and distributing funds and its reduced role in direct service provision reflects a tendency towards the state becoming a “hollow state.” &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989:201)&lt;/span&gt;, meanwhile argues that the expanded role played by the voluntary sector in delivering publicly funded social services has led to the formation of “a shadow state … a para-state apparatus with collective service responsibilities previously shouldered by the public sector, administered outside democratic politics, but yet controlled in both formal and informal ways by the state.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political support for the voluntary sector to assume an increased role in delivering social services has come from both the right and the left. Conservative arguments call for “mediating institutions” such as voluntary organizations to play a more active role in social service in order to guard against and reduce undue government interference into the private lives of the citizenry.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Progressive arguments position voluntary sector social service provision as an addition to rather than a replacement for public social welfare services and as a means for people to assume more autonomy over the welfare of their communities.&lt;a href=&quot;#fn3&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; While the latter view paints a rosy picture in which voluntary sector social services increase the stock of social welfare and further the realization of social justice in a given community, the literature identifies several issues which collectively suggest that devolution from the state to the community may have the opposite effect by reducing access to basic entitlements and necessary social services by vulnerable segments of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;Salamon (1995)&lt;/span&gt; identifies four forms of “voluntary failure” that may render the voluntary sector ill-equipped to take on responsibility for welfare provision in the absence of state support. For one, as organizations reliant upon voluntary contributions, non-profit social service agencies would face difficulties in securing the funds required to deliver vital social services. A potentially significant source of non-state funding is from tax-deductible donations made by wealthy individuals, foundations, and corporations. However, relying upon these sources is problematic given that these donors often prefer to donate to arts and cultural organizations and educational institutions than to social services organizations that work in marginalized communities. Furthermore, reliance upon wealthy donors may usher in a form of “philanthropic paternalism” &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;(Salamon 1995 PAGE)&lt;/span&gt; as the donors who foot large portions of the bill for social service programming may make their contributions conditional in order to shape the content of services and programs as well as criteria defining target groups who are eligible to access these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, foregoing large donations and relying upon communities of service users to fund the costs of the services they access through small donations or user fees presents its own issues. While this approach may be beneficial in furthering local control over the provision of social welfare services in a community, in practice service levels would likely be inadequate in economically marginalized communities. The same shortage of income and assets that makes social services necessary in the first place would make it unlikely that community members requiring these services would have the resources to pay for their provision. Finally, periods of economic downturn would be especially problematic for social service agencies reliant upon private contributions. At such times, when an increased proportion of the population requires access to social welfare supports, agencies’ ability to procure funding from user fees and individual donations would be further reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-geiger1986&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geiger, R. K. and J. R. Wolch. 1986. “A Shadow State? Voluntarism in Metropolitan Los Angeles.” &lt;em&gt;Environment and Planning D: Society and Space&lt;/em&gt; 4(3):351–66.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-hall1998&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hall, Michael H. and Paul B. Reed. 1998. “Shifting the Burden: How Much Can Government Download to the Nonprofit Sector?” &lt;em&gt;Canadian Public Administration&lt;/em&gt; 41(1):1–20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-milward1994&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milward, H. Brinton. 1994. “Nonprofit Contracting and the Hollow State.” &lt;em&gt;Public Administration Review&lt;/em&gt; 54(1):73.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-salamon1993&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salamon, Lester M. 1993. “The Marketization of Welfare: Changing Nonprofit and For-Profit Roles in the American Welfare State.” &lt;em&gt;Social Service Review&lt;/em&gt; 67(1):16–39.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-salamon1995-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salamon, Lester M. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Partners in Public Service : Government-Nonprofit Relations in the Modern Welfare State&lt;/em&gt;. Baltimore, Md: Johns Hopkins University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-wolch1989&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wolch, Jennifer. 1989. “The Shadow State : Transformations in the Voluntary Sector.” Pp. 197–221 in &lt;em&gt;The power of geography : How territory shapes social life&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jennifer R. Wolch and Michael J. Dear. Boston: Unwin Hyman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Insert references: &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1993&quot;&gt;Salamon (1993)&lt;/span&gt; with national statistics; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;hall1998&quot;&gt;Hall and Reed (1998)&lt;/span&gt; with Canadian data; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;geiger1986&quot;&gt;Geiger and Wolch (1986)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989)&lt;/span&gt; with local data on Los Angeles.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn2&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A means to fill gaps in a scaled down welfare state. Also arguments about efficiency, increasing consumer choice, allowing for market competition, not stifling private initiative &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;(Wolch 1989:200–201)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn3&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A means to provide additional social services above and beyond those provided by an encompassing welfare state. Potential for participatory democracy, local control over community welfare, flexibility to meet community needs in creative ways, more accountable to service users than massive, hierarchical state bureaucracies &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;(Wolch 1989:201–2)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/proposal-draft&quot;&gt;Voluntary Sector Social Service Provision&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Kevin Schachter at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Confessions of a Futbol Revolutionist&lt;/a&gt; on March 22, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Social Justice through the Shadow State: Examining the Progressive Potential of Delivering Social Welfare Supports through the Non-profit Sector]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/proposal-outline" />
  <id>/proposal-outline</id>
  <published>2015-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Kevin Schachter</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kevinschachter@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dawn of the neoliberal era in the last decades of the 20th century ushered in a fundamental restructuring of the state apparatus, notably including a retrenchment of the public social welfare regimes that had been developed earlier in the century. A primary means by which restructuring has occurred is through devolution of responsibility for social services from the state to the private and non-profit sectors. According to &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989:217)&lt;/span&gt;, this devolution has led to the formation of a “shadow state apparatus” consisting of non-governmental organizations that are endowed with responsibility to provide collective social welfare supports and are situated outside of the statutory welfare regime. While &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;wolch1989&quot;&gt;Wolch (1989:202)&lt;/span&gt; finds that theorists from across the political spectrum have advocated for non-governmental organizations to assume a greater role in delivering social welfare supports, the literature abounds with criticisms which highlight that a primary motivation for and effect of devolution is to support the ongoing neoliberal project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;critiques-of-devolution&quot;&gt;Critiques of Devolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decrease in social welfare
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some geographic areas and organizations have greater access to resources and services than others, while vulnerable communities may have less access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reliance upon user fees is especially problematic for vulnerable communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier to withdraw funding from NGOs than to eliminate direct government programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reduces government accountability for social inequality and associated problems &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;macdonald2011&quot;&gt;(MacDonald 2011)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Furthers the colonization of society with neoliberal ways of being
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizations must compete for funding
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Branding and marketing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business and entrepreneurial activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restrictions on activities in order to remain fundable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NGO industrial complex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress on efficiency
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower wages and costs than public sector employment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible labour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourages the development of neoliberal dispositions among citizens accessing supports
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model of self-help instead of public welfare and basic entitlement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;progressive-potential&quot;&gt;Progressive Potential&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May increase local autonomy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Political clout of the voluntary sector could pressure the state for increased entitlements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could extend the range of social welfare services available rather than fill service gaps caused by retrenchment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can mobilize resistance among vulnerable groups and advocates of social justice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human-scale, community organizations rather than “iron cage” government bureaucracies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;research-question&quot;&gt;Research Question&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This project will assess the progressive potential of delivering social welfare supports through the non-profit sector, and explicate factors that contribute to and counteract the voluntary sector’s capacity to work for progressive social change.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can non-profit social welfare organizations contribute to broader social transformation beyond immediate service delivery?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can shadow state organizations deliver services in a manner that is compatible with a broader vision for social change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What factors contribute to and counteract the non-profit sector’s capacity to contribute to progressive social change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the benefits and drawbacks of delivering social welfare services/supports through the voluntary sector?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there additional benefits to service recipients that derive from accessing supports from non-profit organizations rather than from government institutions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;theoretical-lens&quot;&gt;Theoretical Lens&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will draw upon and apply two theories of radical social change to assess the progressive potential of providing social welfare supports through the non-profit sector: strategic and prefigurative politics.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategic:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What factors contribute to and counteract the sector’s capacity to advocate for systemic, structural change in government programs and policies?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefigurative:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What factors contribute to and counteract the sector’s capacity to contribute towards changes in the everyday lives of community members, including cultural and relational transformation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To what extent can prefigurative politics be practiced in the shadow state?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there an affinity between prefigurative politics and the model of social change being practiced by social welfare NGOs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the devolution of social welfare service provision to the voluntary sector provide additional opportunities for the practice of prefigurative politics in the process of service deliver?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tension between these two theories concerning the role that formal organizations should play in efforts to achieve radical social change.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can non-profit social welfare service providers be leveraged by movements for radical social change?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This project will draw upon a qualititative research methodology and employ three research methods:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literature review
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Synthesizing and connecting literature on the benefits and drawbacks of devolving social welfare services to the shadow state, and how devolution can contribute to or counteract the realization of social justice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literature on:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The shadow state and social service devolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radical social change, prefigurative politics, participatory democracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People-centered systems / systems that work well from the perspective of the user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autoethnography
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An autoethnographical analysis of my experience developing and delivering social welfare programs to low-income communities as a program co-ordinator at SEED Winnipeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informal expert interviews
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informal expert interviews with program delivery staff and directors at SEED Winnipeg, who have experience developing, managing, and delivering community-based social welfare programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-macdonald2011&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacDonald, Fiona. 2011. “Indigenous Peoples and Neoliberal Privatization in Canada: Opportunities, Cautions and Constraints.” &lt;em&gt;Canadian Journal of Political Science/Revue canadienne de science politique&lt;/em&gt; 44(02):257–73.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-wolch1989&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wolch, Jennifer. 1989. “The Shadow State : Transformations in the Voluntary Sector.” Pp. 197–221 in &lt;em&gt;The power of geography : How territory shapes social life&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Jennifer R. Wolch and Michael J. Dear. Boston: Unwin Hyman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/proposal-outline&quot;&gt;Social Justice through the Shadow State: Examining the Progressive Potential of Delivering Social Welfare Supports through the Non-profit Sector&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Kevin Schachter at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Confessions of a Futbol Revolutionist&lt;/a&gt; on December 14, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>